A Guide to the John Skelton Williams Papers, 1884-1926
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
John Skelton Williams Papers, 1884-1926
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
10040, 10040-a
This collection consists of ca. 26,000 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The Williams papers were a gift to the University by Hubert L. Williams, Hinsdale, Illinois, through John Skelton Williams, Jr., Richmond, Virginia, on February 3, 1975 and August 1, 1975.
Biographical/Historical Information
Born in Powhatan County, Virginia, on July 6, 1865, John Skelton Williams was one of several children of John Langbourne and Maria (Skelton) Williams. He was educated in private schools in Richmond and briefly studied law at the University of Virginia. While he was still a very young man, he was taken into partnership with his father in the firm of John L. Williams and Sons. In 1895 he married Lila Lefebvre Issacs, by whom he had two sons, John Jr. and Hubert. In that same year he began the formation of the Seaboard Air Line Railway system, which was a short route between New York and Florida, out of a number of smaller railroads. Completing the merger in 1900, he became president of the new railroad at the age of thirty-four. In 1903, however, after a bitter struggle with Thomas Fortune Ryan and other New York financiers, he was forced out of the presidency. He struggled for many years to regain control of the railroad, while continuing to be heavily involved in investment ventures, especially in the South. He served as the president of several smaller railways, the Bank of Richmond, the Southern Investment Company, and as director of other banks, trust companies, railroads, and corporations. Williams' involvement in politics in this period appears to have been minimal, though he was a Democrat.
In March 1913, Williams was appointed assistant secretary of the treasury by Woodrow Wilson at the request of Secretary McAdoo, and in January 1914, he was named Comptroller of the Currency. As comptroller, Williams was a member ex officio of the committee which set up the new Federal Reserve system, and was also a member of the Interstate Commerce Commission's advisory board on valuation. When McAdoo became director-general of the railroads in December 1917, Williams became his director of finance and purchases, a position which he held until March 1919. Wilson appointed Williams to the Central Committee of the American Red Cross in October 1918, and he was subsequently elected its treasurer in December of that year.
Williams performed his official duties with zeal and efficiency, and his determination and inflexible sense of justice won him many powerful enemies. He attacked the concentration of banking power in the hands of a few and accused several national banks of usury. The officials of the Riggs National Bank in Washington, D.C. were found guilty of irregular practices after a series of law suits initiated by Williams.
Williams's last two years in office were embroiled in controversy as his opponents attempted to block confirmation of his reappointment to the controllership in the Senate. Neither the earlier recommendation to confirm nor a later recommendation to reject the nomination was acted upon by the Senate as a whole. In March 1921, Williams resigned his office due to the imminent accession of a hostile Republican administration.
Shortly after he left office, Williams charged that the Federal Reserve Board had by its deflationary policies caused the terrible decline in agricultural prices which began in 1920 and attacked several of the Federal Reserve Banks fro their expenditures for buildings and salaries. His accusations formed the basis of a congressional investigation which sustained some of his charges against the Board. Subsequently, Williams returned to Richmond and served as the chairman of the board of directors of the Richmond Trust Company until his sudden death in 1926.
Williams correspondence documents the striking continuity in his career; for both as investment banker and comptroller of the currency he displayed a love of justice and respect for the individual.
Scope and Content Information
The John Skelton Williams papers consist of ca. 26,000 items, (ca. 40 linear feet) 1884-1926, concerning Williams' varied career as a businessman and public servant in the administration of Woodrow Wilson. Including business, political, and family correspondence and papers, speeches, newspaper clippings, photographs, and other items, the collection in valuable in the study of American business and finance, particularly of railroads, 1899-1913, and of governmental, economic and financial policies, 1913-1921.
The bulk of the business correspondence related to Williams involvement with the Seaboard Air Line Railway and various smaller railways, investment banking interests, and stock ventures, such as controlling interests in fertilizer, sulphur-deposit mining, and oil companies. Williams G. McAdoo, Thomas Fortune Ryan, and Bernard M. Baruch. The business papers consist of pamphlets, circulars, lists and legal documents, many of them concerning the Seaboard Air Lin Railway. Williams' tenure of office, briefly as assistant secretary of the treasury, and for seven years as comptroller of the currency, provides the subject for the political correspondence. The controversial character of his public service is reflected in the amount of material related to his lawsuits against the Riggs National Bank of Washington, D.C. and his principal topics of interest in the correspondence in this period are Williams' work with the Federal Reserve Board, the administration of the railroads during World War I, and the American Red Cross. He was particularly concerned to keep the national banks in as sound and stable a condition as possible. Williams corresponded with other government officials and politicians, such as Woodrow Wilson, Warren Harding, Carter Glass, Claude Swanson, William G. McAdoo, George Foster Peabody, Walker D. Hines, William J. Bryan, W. P. G. Harding and many others. The letterbooks for the years 1918-1919 and 1921-1922 have many memoranda, minutes of meetings, affidavits, and official reports. Many letters document Williams' efforts to draw public attention to abuses in the Federal Reserve system, 1921-1922, following his resignation from office.
The family correspondence includes letters written to and from Williams, his wife Lila, his brothers, Alfred B., Langbourne M., W. Berkeley, Ennion G., R. Lancaster, E. Randolph, father, John L., mother, Maria S., sons John, Jr. and Herbert and other relatives and friends. The bulk of the correspondence is between Lila and her sons.
The correspondence as a whole is sharply differentiated: there is virtually no political correspondence prior to Williams' appointment in early 1913, and since he held no directorships in any companies from this time on until 1921, the business correspondence from 1913-1926 is very sparse. There is virtually no material reflecting Williams' business activities, 1921-1926.
Arrangement
Arrangement
The main accession number of this collection (#10,040) and its addition (#10,040-a) have been interfiled. Some of the correspondence was roughly in alphabetical order by year, so it was decided to impose this order upon the business and political correspondence.
Organization
The collection is divided into five series:
Series I: 1899-1926 - Business and Political Correspondence.
Within each year, the letters have been arranged alphabetically by correspondent. There are several folders arranged by topics, such as the construction of "Paxton," Williams' home, Williams' confirmation.
Series II: 1884-1925-The family correspondence is in chronological order.
Series III: 1888-1926 - The business papers are in chronological order.
Series IV: 1913-1924 - Political papers have been arranged chronologically.
Series V: ca. 1900-1926- Family papers have been arranged by topic.
Series VI: 1892- 1926 - Miscellaneous
a: 1892-1921 -Speeches by Williams or his wife have been placed in chronological order.
b. 1899-1946 - Newspapers clippings are in chronological order.
c. ca. 1900-1926 - Photographs, Greeting Cards, Biological Sketches.
d. 1899-1922 - The letterbooks including business and political letters have been placed in chronological order.
3. 1914-1919 - Scrapbook of Newspaper Clippings
Contents List
- 1899-1926 - Business and Political Correspondence
  - Business Correspondence 1899-1901, 75 items. 3 folders. (Box 1)
  - Business Correspondence, A-Sh 1902, 965 items. 4 folders. (Box 1)
  - Business Correspondence, Sm-Y 1902, 249 items. 2 folders. (Box 2)
  - Business Correspondence, A-R 1903, 359 items. 3 folders. (Box 2)
  - Business Correspondence, S-Z 1903, 221 items. 2 folders. (Box 3)
  - Correspondence Record - Index of Williams' Correspondents 1903, Oversize Ledger
  - Business Correspondence, A-L 1904, 327 items. 4 folders. (Box 3)
  - Business Correspondence, Mc-W 1904, 322 items. 5 folders. (Box 4)
  - Correspondence Record - Index of Williams' Correspondents 1904, Oversize Ledger
  - Business Correspondence, A 1905, 59 items. (Box 4)
  - Business Correspondence, B-J 1905, 422 items. 5 folders. (Box 5)
  - Business Correspondence, L-Se 1905, 500 items. 5 folders. (Box 6)
  - Business Correspondence, Sh-Y 1905, 211 items. 3 folders. (Box 7)
  - Correspondence Record - Index of Williams' Correspondents 1905-1905, Oversize Ledger
  - Business Correspondence, A-C 1906, 282 items. 3 folders. (Box 7)
  - Business Correspondence, D-L 1906, 581 items. 5 folders. (Box 8)
  - Business Correspondence, Mc-N 1906, 533 items. 5 folders. (Box 9)
  - Business Correspondence, O-Wh 1906, 454 items. 5 folders. (Box 10)
  - Business Correspondence, Wi-Y 1906, 102 items. (Box 11)
  - Business Correspondence, A-E 1907, 351 items. 4 folders. (Box 11)
  - Business Correspondence, F-Mey 1907, 435 items. 5 folders. (Box 12)
  - Business Correspondence, Mid-Sy 1907, 514 items. 6 folders. (Box 13)
  - Business Correspondence, T-Y 1907, 201 items. 2 folders. (Box 14)
  - Business Correspondence, A-Ch 1908, 229 items. 2 folders. (Box 14)
  - Business Correspondence, Ci-H 1908, 321 items. 5 folders. (Box 15)
  - Business Correspondence, I-P 1908, 525 items. 5 folders. (Box 16)
  - Business Correspondence, R-Z 1908, 635 items. 6 folders. (Box 17)
  - Business Correspondence, A-D 1909, 518 items. 5 folders. (Box 18)
  - Business Correspondence, E-Ma 1909, 535 items. 5 folders. (Box 19)
  - Business Correspondence, Me-Por 1909, 499 items. 6 folders. (Box 20)
  - Business Correspondence, Pr-Williams, C. T. 1909, 533 items. 7 folders. (Box 21)
  - Business Correspondence, Williams, E. L. - Z 1909, 281 items. 4 folders. (Box 22)
  - Business Correspondence, A-Ha 1910, 554 items. 6 folders. (Box 23)
  - Business Correspondence, He-Sk 1910, 561 items. 5 folders. (Box 24)
  - Business Correspondence, Sm-Wy 1910, 362 items. 5 folders. (Box 25)
  - Correspondence related to the construction of "Paxton," home of J.S. Williams 1910, 9 items. (Box 25)
  - Business Correspondence, A-Ca 1911, 494 items. 6 folders. (Box 26)
  - Business Correspondence, Ce-Gi 1911, 391 items. 5 folders. (Box 27)
  - Business Correspondence, Go-L 1911, 446 items. 5 folders. (Box 28)
  - Business Correspondence, Mc-Q 1911, 533 items. 5 folders. (Box 29)
  - Business Correspondence, R-T 1911, 454 items. 5 folders. (Box 30)
  - Business Correspondence, U-Z 1911, 365 items. 4 folders. (Box 31)
  - Correspondence related to the construction of "Paxton," home of John Skelton Williams 1911, 90 items. (Box 31)
  - Papers Related to the Construction of "Paxton," home of John Skelton Williams 1911, 1 items. (Box 31)
  - Business Correspondence, Ac-D 1912, 443 items. 7 folders. (Box 32)
  - Business Correspondence, Ea-L 1912, 546 items. 6 folders. (Box 33)
  - Business Correspondence, Mc-R 1912, 686 items. 7 folders. (Box 34)
  - Business Correspondence, Sa- Williams, C. T. 1912, 561 items. 6 folders. (Box 35)
  - Business Correspondence, Williams, C.T. - Young 1912, 224 items. 3 folders. (Box 36)
  - Correspondence related to the construction of "Paxton," home of J.S. Williams 1912, 333 items. 5 folders. (Box 37)
  - Blueprints and drawings related to the construction of "Paxton," home of J.S. Williams 1912, 12 items. (Box 37)
  - Papers related to the construction of "Paxton," home of J.S. Williams 1912, 35 items. (Box 37)
  - Business Correspondence, A-Sim 1913, 381 items. 6 folders. (Box 38)
  - Business Correspondence, So-W 1913, 87 items. 2 folders. (Box 39)
  - Political Correspondence 1913, 32 items. (Box 39)
  - Political Correspondence, A-J 1914, 193 items. 3 folders. (Box 39)
  - Political Correspondence, L-Y 1914, 148 items. 4 folders. (Box 40)
  - Business Correspondence 1914, 2 items. (Box 40)
  - Political Correspondence 1915, 5 items. (Box 41)
  - Business Correspondence 1915, 1 items. (Box 41)
  - Political Correspondence 1916-1917, 77 items. 2 folders. (Box 41)
  - Business Correspondence 1917, 1 items. (Box 41)
  - Political Correspondence, A-Bl 1918, 115 items. 2 folders. (Box 41)
  - Political Correspondence, Bo-Y 1918, 273 items. 5 folders. (Box 42)
  - Business Correspondence 1918, 18 items. (Box 42)
  - Political Correspondence, A-W 1919, 95 items. 2 folders. (Box 43)
  - Political Correspondence related to Williams' Confirmation, A-P 1919, 127 items. 3 folders. (Box 43)
  - Political Correspondence related to Williams' Confirmation, R-W 1919, 51 items. (Box 44)
  - Political Correspondence related to Williams' Confirmation: Commendatory letters from banks 1919, 52 items. (Box 44)
  - Political Correspondence related to Williams' Confirmation: Commendatory letters from banks, Alabama-Wyoming 1919 Nov.-Dec., 203 items. 2 folders. (Box 44)
  - Political Correspondence related to Williams' Confirmation: Commendatory letters from banks 1919 Dec. - 1920 Jan., 130 items. 2 folders. (Box 44)
  - Political Correspondence related to Williams' Confirmation: Commendatory letters from individuals 1919, 56 items. (Box 44)
  - Business Correspondence 1919, 31 items. (Box 44)
  - Political Correspondence, A-W 1920, 289 items. 5 folders. (Box 45)
  - Political Correspondence related to Williams' Confirmation 1920, 29 items. (Box 46)
  - Political Correspondence related to Williams' Confirmation: Commendatory letters from Congressmen 1920, 58 items. (Box 46)
  - Political Correspondence related to Williams' Confirmation: Commendatory letters from Federal Reserve Bank executives and directors 1920, 33 items. (Box 46)
  - Political Correspondence related to Williams' Confirmation: Commendatory letters from Senators 1920, 26 items. (Box 46)
  - Political Correspondence: Williams' letters to the Federal Reserve Board 1920-1921, 1 items. (Box 46)
  - Business Correspondence, A-W 1920, 42 items. 3 folders. (Box 46)
  - Political Correspondence, A-W 1921, 88 items. 4 folders. (Box 47)
  - Political Correspondence 1922, 15 items. (Box 47)
  - Political Correspondence
  - Business Correspondence 1922, 2 items. (Box 48)
  - Political Correspondence 1923, 5 items. (Box 48)
  - Business Correspondence 1923, 1 item. (Box 48)
  - Political Correspondence 1924, 1 item. (Box 48)
  - Business Correspondence 1924, 2 items. (Box 48)
  - Political Correspondence 1925, 1 item. (Box 48)
  - Business Correspondence 1925, 4 items. (Box 48)
  - Political Correspondence including letters from William Jennings Bryan n.d., 6 items. (Box 48)
  - Business Correspondence n.d., 2 items. (Box 48)
- 1884-1925 - Family Correspondence
  - Family Correspondence 1884, 1895, 1896, 1897, 6 items. (Box 49)
  - Family Correspondence 1902, 15 items. (Box 49)
  - Family Correspondence 1904-1906, 5 items. (Box 49)
  - Family Correspondence 1908-1915, 153 items. 8 folders. (Box 49)
  - Family Correspondence 1916-1917, 168 items. 6 folders. (Box 50)
  - Family Correspondence 1917-1918, 141 items. 5 folders. (Box 51)
  - Family Correspondence 1919-1920, 109 items. 4 folders. (Box 52)
  - Family Correspondence 1920, 103 items. 4 folders. (Box 53)
  - Family Correspondence 1921, 130 items. 5 folders. (Box 54)
  - Family Correspondence
  - Family Correspondence 1922, 145 items. 6 folders. (Box 55)
  - Family Correspondence 1923, 132 items. 5 folders. (Box 56)
  - Family Correspondence 1924, 164 items. 6 folders. (Box 57)
  - Family Correspondence 1926-1926, 32 items. 2 folders. (Box 58)
  - Family Correspondence n.d., 74 items. 2 folders. (Box 58)
- 1888-1926 - Business Papers
  - Business Papers: A Manual of Investments compiled and published by John L. Williams & Son 1888, 1 item. (Box 59)
  - Business Papers: A Manual of Investments compiled and published by John L. Williams & Son 1889-1890, 2 items. (Box 59)
  - Business Papers 1898-1901, 36 items. 5 folders. (Box 60)
  - Business Papers [1901?], 1 item. (Box 60)
  - Business Papers 1902, 10 items. (Box 60)
  - Business Papers 1903-1904, 137 items. 5 folders. (Box 61)
  - Business Papers: Court Plea vs. Ryan Control of Seaboard Voting Trust 1904, 1 item. (Box 62)
  - Business Papers 1904-1905, 121 items. 5 folders. (Box 62)
  - Business Papers 1905-1907, 151 items. 5 folders. (Box 63)
  - Business Papers 1908-1910, 148 items. 6 folders. (Box 64)
  - Business Papers 1910, 113 items. 2 folders. (Box 65)
  - Business Papers [1910?], 2 items. (Box 65)
  - Business Papers 1911, 160 items. (Box 65)
  - Business Papers 1911-1912, 239 items. 6 folders. (Box 66)
  - Business Papers 1912, 366 items. 6 folders. (Box 67)
  - Business Papers 1913, 106 items. 3 folders. (Box 68)
  - Business Papers 1915-1919, 93 items. 5 folders. (Box 68)
  - Business Papers 1920, 12 items. (Box 69)
  - Business Papers 1922, 1 item. (Box 69)
  - Business Papers 1926, 2 items. (Box 69)
  - Business Papers n.d., 35 items. (Box 69)
  - Business Papers: Diary of appointments 1898-1901, 4 items. (Box 70)
  - Business Papers: Diary of appointments 1902-1904, 3 items. (Box 71)
  - Business Papers: Diary of appointments 1906, 1 item. (Box 71)
  - Business Papers: Diary of appointments 1907, 1 item. (Box 72)
  - Business Papers: Diary of appointments 1909-1912, 4 items. (Box 72)
  - Ledger, John L. Williams & Son 1903-1904, 1 item. (Box 73)
  - Index to subject files n.d., 2 items. (Box 73)
- 1913-1924
  Political Papers
  - Political Papers: The Aldrich Monetary Commission Bill - The Federal Reserve Act 1913, 1 item. (Box 74)
  - Political Papers 1913, 34 items. 5 folders. (Box 74)
  - Rural Credits, joint hearings before the sub committee on currency & banking 1914, 1 item. (Box 74)
  - Annual Report of the Secretary of the Navy 1915, 1 item. (Box 74)
  - Political Papers: Affidavit of Williams in the Riggs National Bank Case 1915, 1 item. (Box 75)
  - Political Papers: Affidavit and Answer of Williams in the Riggs National Bank Case 1915, 1 item. (Box 75)
  - Political Papers: Affidavit and Answer of McAdoo in the Riggs National Bank Case 1915, 3 items. (Box 75)
  - Political Papers: Miscellaneous letters relating to correspondence between the Treasury Department and the Riggs National Bank 1915, 1 item. (Box 75)
  - Political Papers 1916, 4 items. (Box 75)
  - Political Papers: Transcript of trial, The United States vs officials of the Riggs National Bank (Tenth Day) 1916, 1 item. (Box 75)
  - Political Papers: Justice Department press release on the Riggs National Bank Case 1916, 1 item. (Box 75)
  - Political Papers: Transcript of trial, The United States vs officials of the Riggs National Bank (Eleventh Day) 1916, 1 item. (Box 75)
  - Political Papers: Investigation of usury charges against banks, Hearings before the Committee on Rules 1916, 1 item. (Box 75)
  - Annual Report of the Comptroller of the currency 1916, 1 item. (Box 76)
  - A Brief for the establishment of Muscle Shoals on the Tennessee River 1916, 1 item. (Box 76)
  - Political Papers 1917-1918, 66 items. 3 folders. (Box 76)
  - Political Papers: Brief in the case of First National Bank vs J.S. Williams 1919, 1 item. (Box 77)
  - Political Papers 1919, 30 items. (Box 77)
  - Political Papers related to Williams' confirmation [1919?], 1 item. (Box 77)
  - Political Papers related to Williams' confirmation 1919, 13 items. 2 folders. (Box 77)
  - Political Papers related to Williams' confirmation: complication of commendatory letters 1919, 6 items. (Box 77)
  - Nomination of John S. Williams Comptroller of the Currency, Hearing before the Committee on Banking and Currency United States Senate 1919, 1 item. (Box 78)
  - Testimony on the nomination of the Comptroller of the Currency 1919, 1 item. (Box 78)
  - Political Papers related to Williams' confirmation, Hearings before the Committee on Banking and Currency of the U.S. Senate 1919, 9 items. 7 folders. (Box 79)
  - Political Papers related to Williams' confirmation 1919, 12 items. (Box 80)
  - Political Papers related to Williams' confirmation [1919?], 1 item. (Box 80)
  - Political Papers 1920, 26 items. (Box 80)
  - Political Papers related to Williams' confirmation 1920, 9 items. (Box 80)
  - Report of the Postmaster General 1920, 1 item. (Box 80)
  - Annual Report of the Comptroller of the Currency 1921, 1 item. (Box 81)
  - Agricultural Inquiry: Hearing before the Joint Commission of Agricultural Inquiry 1921, 2 items. (Box 81)
  - Political Papers 1921, 25 items. (Box 81)
  - Political Papers: Commerce and Finance magazine, with article "The Administration of the Federal Reserve System" by J. S. Williams 1921, 1 item. (Box 81)
  - Political Papers related to Williams' views on the administration of the Federal Reserve Board 1922, 12 items. 2 folders. (Box 81)
  - Political Papers 1923-1924, 2 items. (Box 81)
  - Political Papers n.d., 9 items. (Box 81)
- ca. 1900-1926
  Family Papers
  - Family Papers: School Papers of John, Jr. and Hubert Williams ca. 1900-1926, n.d., 48 items. (Box 82)
  - Family Papers: Mementoes and Miscellaneous Notes ca. 1900-1926, n.d., 18 items. (Box 82)
  - Family Papers: Notes and Miscellaneous items ca. 1900-1926, n.d., 19 items. (Box 82)
  - Family Papers: Mementoes and Miscellaneous Notes ca. 1900-1926, n.d., 7 items. (Box 82)
  - Family Papers Souvenirs and Mementoes ca. 1900-1926, n.d., 64 items. (Box 82)
  - Family Papers: Legal Documents, Mementoes ca. 1900-1926, n.d., 3 items. (Box 82)
  - Family Papers: Notes in shorthand n.d., 3 items. (Box 82)
  - Family Papers: Pamphlets written by John L. Williams 1915, n.d., 5 items. (Box 83)
  - Family Papers: Report Cards of John, Jr. and Hubert S. Williams 1915-1916, 12 items. (Box 83)
  - Family Papers: Southern Medical Journal, with article by Ennion G. Williams 1918, 1 item. (Box 83)
  - Family Papers: Washington Social Register 1919, 1 item. (Box 83)
  - Family Papers related to the consular career of J. S. Williams, Jr. 1921-1923, 12 items. (Box 83)
  - Family Papers: "Commonplace Book" of John L. Williams ca. 1877-1915, 1 item. (Box 83)
- 1892-1926
  Miscellaneous
  - 1892-1921 Speeches by Williams or his wife have been placed in chronological order
    - Speeches 1892, 3 items. (Box 84)
    - Speeches 1902, 1 item. (Box 84)
    - Speeches 1907-1910, 13 items. 5 folders. (Box 84)
    - Speeches 1912-1913, 3 items. 2 folders. (Box 84)
    - Speeches 1914-1917, 22 items. 5 folders. (Box 85)
    - Speeches 1919-1921, 12 items. 3 folders. (Box 86)
    - Speeches n.d., 5 items. (Box 86)
    - Toast before the Gridiron Club [?] n.d., 1 item. (Box 86)
    - Miscellaneous notes for speeches n.d., 8 items. (Box 86)
    - Speech by L. L. W. [Lila L. Williams] n.d., 1 item. (Box 86)
    - Speech by L. L. W. [Lila L. Williams] n.d., 1 item. (Box 86)
  - 1899-1946 - Newspaper Clippings
    - Newspaper clippings related to Williams 1899, 2 items. (Box 87)
    - Newspaper clippings 1904-1905, 2 items. 2 folders. (Box 87)